As I said welcome back and today in part
two of distributed logging we are going
to cover some very very important part
of it appenders. Okay. So the
prerequisite is part one of distributed
logging because there we have seen the
internal framework of logger like what
is SLF 4J log back log 4j2 its
architecture both high level and low
level we have seen how to create a
logger object different logger levels
how logger framework uses it parent
child hierarchy root logger very very
important okay and this is a very very
big topic So and lot of interview
questions plus in day-to-day work we use
this logging heavily. Okay. So I will
try to cover each possible topic
subtopic of it. So sorry if this
stretches a bit because this is
something which I don't want to skip any
subtopic. Okay. So let's start with the
part two of it which is appenders.
Okay. So my understanding is you have
already seen the part one and that's
where I'm start uh starting with the
appenders itself so that you know where
this appender fit into this highle
design itself.
Okay. So appender is the component that
decides where the log will go whether
the log will be shown to console or save
to file DB Kafka etc. Where the locks
will go that is decided by appender and
this was the highle design just to
recall what we have seen in the part one
where the appender exactly sit. So we
have SLF 4j which is nothing but an
interface. We have log back and log 4j
which is nothing but an implementation.
They make use of appender. You can say
that this is a helper.
So this implementation make use of
appender to decide
where the log statement will go whether
the console your file DB etc and
aggregation tools uses this output where
the log statements are going and shows
the logging.
Okay. So till now we just created logger
object and also seen how to override its
level through application.properties. We
have already seen that we have created
an object through logger and also we
know that the default level is info and
through application.properties
we can override this also and we ran our
application and invoke the endpoint
properly. We have seen that and we see
that the logs are properly printed on
the console. So we ended the part one
with the question that
we have not used any appender here. So
how come the output is shown to console
because what we understood is the
appender is the one who decide where the
output will go. So we have seen that the
parent child hierarchy that let's say uh
this is our class this is our logger
right uh payment controller. So it's
package com do.concepts concepts dotp
payment controller that would be the
name of the logger and it will create a
package com.concepts concepts
com.concepts concept dotp payment
controller we have already seen this in
depth in the previous so that's why I am
just recalling it a little fast because
this is needed for appender
so even though we have not write any
appender here for our logger payments
controller what it will do is by default
it will check the parent appender so
here we have any append no it will check
its parent any appender no goes to the
root level root level uh root level
logger always has one default appender
console. So because of that we are able
to see our log on console.
Okay.
So till now I think
it might have helped you in recalling
what we have done in the previous video.
Okay, very quick. But yeah, now we see
that how to write appenders for our
logger.
Please note conceptually both logback
and log 4j2 use appenders to define
where the logs will go but that differs
little in syntax. Mostly all the things
which we are going to see in the
appenders right both uses with similar
purpose. Okay, but there are some little
difference in the syntax that's all. So
I will not cover both like how to write
appenders in log back, how to write
appenders in log 4j2. So I will cover
the log back which is default for spring
boot and also very popular too. Okay,
but even if you switch to log 4j2 almost
similar very minor difference in the
syntax but conceptually everything is
same.
So let's see that the first thing we
have to do is we have to create a file
logbackrint.xml
which should exist in the path source/
main/resource under resources folder we
have to write this file. So the naming
convention we have to follow because
spring framework springboard framework
try to look for this file name itself.
So this file contains all the
information about our appenders like
loggers, root logger and the pattern. We
will see that how. So this is a very
basic syntax of logback spring.xml.
So here if you see it start with
configuration and the file end with end
of the configurations. Okay. And between
that the first thing we have is
appender. We can have many appender.
Appender one, appender two till appender
end. Okay. So this is one appender. So
appender the name whatever the name you
want to give to an appender you can give
the class. Okay. Uh because in the
appender what is the logic? It decide
where the log statement will go. Whether
you have to save in DB, whether you have
to save in Kafka. So there should be
some logic right. So the class so this
is a class which for this appender name
whenever this appender name is used this
class will get invoked.
Then we have something called encoder.
Within encoder we have pattern. So now
see appender decide where the log will
go. Encoder decide its format how it
will look. Okay. So don't worry encoder
I will cover separately in the below in
this part itself but there is a
difference appender decide
where the log will go whether DB Kafka
or your uh file console but encoder
again I'm saying encoder decide how
it will look or you can say that its
format okay so currently this is one
format you will see date then you will
see level then you will see logger name
then the message this is one format
don't worry about this that what is uh
module D what is this uh percentage
level percentage logger I will tell you
later but for now all you have to
understand this encoder decide the
format of the log which is going to
ultimately save into either file or DB
or something which is decided by
appender
Okay. Similarly like this we can have
many appenders we want. So
this file first thing they have is
appender.
The second is loggers. We can have many
loggers. Correct? You know that till now
in the previous video we have seen for
one logger name
one logger object exist. Okay. So for
each name you can say that one logger
name one logger object exist.
So we can have multiple loggers possible
right let's say we have hundred of
classes so for each class it is possible
that we have one logger object so we can
have multiple loggers
so logger the name you wanted to give to
the logger okay the level info want
error we have already seen what level is
okay by default is info and we can also
provide change the level into
application.properties
but here also we can define the level
whether it's an info warn error etc and
also remember let's say that you have
defined the level here in logback spring
doxml also you have defined the level
into application.properties properties
this is more priority. Okay.
So logger name the level additivity true
or false. So
additivity
controls appender propagation only.
If you remember from the hierarchy I
told you that
for this logger for our logger this is
our logger right we created one logger
object. This is the name for this name.
One logger is created and we haven't
write any appender. So by default
it goes upward. It propagate upward and
run their appenders too. So this is the
parent. It doesn't have also appender.
It propagate upward and run its parent
appender to till root level. So till
root level it runs all appenders. Okay.
So currently we don't have any appender
here. We don't have any append here only
root has the appender. So that will get
executed. So that is controlled by
additivity. If you want that behavior
that it should propagate upward for
running the appenders make it true which
is by default otherwise make it false.
Okay. So controls appender propagation
only additivity by default it is true.
When the log is accepted, it start
running all the appenders of the logger
and its parent logger till root. It will
append all the appenders. If you don't
want to execute parent appenders, we can
make it false. The same thing which I
have explained. Okay. So the logger has
name level and additivity
as its properties and also this logger.
So we have created multiple appenders.
So we need to associate the appenders to
the logger. So for this logger I am
associating this appender appender
hyphen ref and the reference you can
give the appender name. Okay. So you can
say that let's say here whatever the
logger name you can associate one
appender with this logger. Okay. So here
I have given let's say appender one got
associated here appender one let's say.
So that got associated with this.
Okay. So this is how generally we
associate the logger with an appender
and we can associate more than one
appender. Right. So here we can have
another appender hyphen ref equals to
let's say some other appender appender
two. So this logger has two appenders.
Similarly we can write as many loggers
we want.
And the last is the root which you can
say that the fallback sometime like it
is not possible to have each and every
logger. Okay. So in generally in
production we have thousands of classes.
We have thousands of classes. So for
each class we can't write one logger.
Okay. So generally that's where
hierarchy comes into the picture that
for parent itself we defined the logger.
Okay. And that would ultimately
applicable for all the ch uh children
loggers also. Okay, that's where the
hierarchy comes into the picture.
So but still sometime we need fall back.
So that's where the root comes into the
picture. So root has one level. Okay,
either you can define whether it's an
info, want error. By default it's always
info but we can have like root level
info want whichever you want and the
appender let's say generally console
okay if you are not writing any of this
XML by default it has one root this
logger which has level info and the
appender reference is console.
Okay, but we can change it like this.
Root level equals to whatever the level
you wanted to provide and the appender
which you want to associate with this
root locker.
So let's see this uh example of this
logback
spring.xml.
So this is my logger object which I am
creating inside a payment controller.
Okay. So logger factory dot get logger
payment controller.class. So here this
will ultimately would be con.concepts
dot payment controller. Okay full path.
So that would be the name of the logger.
Now I am creating one logback
spring.xml.
Okay. Starting and ending with
configuration.
I am writing my first appender.
The appender name I have given is
console. You can give any name you want
the class. So I don't have to write a
class that okay whatever the log I've
got I need to show it on console log
logback framework automatically provide
this class. Okay. So I am reusing that
class. So here console appender class is
already present which work is to display
the logs on the console. Okay. So I am
and you can say that there are
if you don't have to insert in DB if you
don't have to insert in some custom
place like Kafka then there are many
appenders which are automatically
available in this framework. So we can
use that. Okay. So I have given the
class this class already has the logic
to show the logs on the console.
Now I am adding an encoder and the
pattern
like this is how I want to show don't
worry about this pattern I will come
later like what all you can use here
okay but consider that it is a free text
so this would get replaced with a date
this would get replaced with a level
like this okay so don't worry about this
we will come that but remember that this
is just a format in which the logs will
be shown to this place console
and appender close. So this is I have
written one appender. Now I can write
multiple loggers which can use this
appender but for now for now I have
explicitly not written any logger. So
for this payment controller I have not
written any logger
only I have written a parent root
logger. So root level equals to info
appender reference is console. So this
one I have written. So now
see this one these are some important
points. I am I think I have already
explained it but I still want to explain
this because this is where many
engineers goes wrong while implementing
our interviews also.
I have not defined any configuration for
logger.
Okay. So
which appender to use? What is the
logger level etc. So currently we have
not defined anything for our logger. We
have not defined any level. We have not
defined any appender.
So for appender it propagate upward till
root. This is the default behavior and
you know that it is controlled through
additivity. So by default that is true.
So it propagate upward and run their
appenders. So it will first goes to com
dot concepts.
From the previous video you might recall
that okay when we are creating an object
of logger and this is the name. So root
is the like a starting one then it will
create a hierarchy that first com its
logger object would also be created.
Then com dot cononcept this logger
object would also be created and
ultimately com do.concepts dot payment
controller this is the logger object.
Now which logger object we are using for
logging uh that it it will start from
there. Okay. So currently we are at
payments controller. So this one
com.concept.p payment controller this is
a log and we are doing log.info. Okay.
So here if you see log.info info.
Now two things level we have not defined
any level. Second thing is appender
where it would be shown that also we
haven't defined for this. So for
appender
default is true additivity is true. So
it will goes till the root level and run
all its parent appender. So com dot
concept is there any appender present?
No. So nothing will happen. Is there any
appender present? No. appender present
root one we have defined that console
okay so it will print on the console
okay and for level if you haven't
defined the level of your logger it will
inherit the level from the immediate
parent so it's immediate parent have we
defined anything no for this one have we
defined anything no root one we have
defined info
okay so this will inherited this will
also inherit. This will also inherit. So
it will have logger have level info and
this I am doing info. So it is equal or
greater than this. So that would be
accepted. So only accepted logs
uh appender logic will run only accepted
logs it will accept it and look for
appenders and propagate upward till root
by default.
So that's why here in the console we are
able to see this log
even though we haven't defined any
appender for our logger it propagate
upward till reaches till root and since
root level we have defined info. So
that's why over logger also inherited
from parent. So that's why this log is
accepted and in the console we able to
see this. And here if you see the
pattern we have defined into the
appender we have this pattern right. So
that's where this is date
level info logger. This is the logger
name and the message. So this is the
format which is decided by pattern which
we will see later.
Okay. Now let's define the appender for
our logger. So currently we haven't
defined the logger. Now just an example
where we are defining the logger. So the
same example paymentscontroller.class.
So I am defining a logger.
So I have an appender name console.
Again it is printing the logger on the
console
encoder like the how the pattern we can
want we can add it here. Now here I am
writing a logger for my
logger specifically name equals to com
do.concepts.p payment controller. This
one level is info editivity is true.
Addit additivity true means for appender
it will first run its appender and then
all its parent also only for accepted
logs. So accepted log is its level is
info. So any log which has the level
info and above that would get accepted
and appender I have referred is console
this one. And I also have a root which
has level info and appender it has
console the same. So can anybody stop
the video here and tell me like when I
am putting log.info
what would be the behavior here? Pause
it
comment like what would exactly happen
here.
So when I hit this endpoint / payments
and this logger would run log.info info.
So what would happen is
here if you see two times I showed info
law. Why? Because I told you that it
maintain a hierarchy root. Then we have
com
do.concepts and then com dot concepts
dotp payment controller. Okay. So this
is the hierarchy it maintain. So
log.info log is an object of payment
controller one. This one. So it start
from here. It will first is this log
accepted? Yes, it log level is info.
Log.info. This is accepted. Now for the
accepted log, it will reach till root
and run its appender. Why? Because
additivity is true. So first it will run
its appender.
It's console. So it will print on
console. One time it's printed then it
goes up. So have we defined any log for
this appender for this com. concept? No.
So nothing will happen. It will goes to
its parent. Have we defined any appender
for this com logger? No. So it will goes
to its parent root. Any appender present
for this root? For this root? Yes.
Console only. So that's why from the
root also it will come. So two times.
Why? Because addit additivity is true.
So it will run its appender and its
parents also. All its parents also.
So if you make additivity false then
here if you see only one time will come.
But then you have to make sure that when
you make an addit additivity false you
have to make sure that this logger at
least have appender associated with it.
Okay, at least one appender should be
there. Otherwise you won't be able to
see this log get output anywhere.
Okay,
I make editivity false. But here I
purposely make it commented out the
console. So there is no
appender and even it even there is no
appender for this logger and also I make
additivity false means it will it will
not propagate upward itself. So we will
get a warning message. No appender
present in the context.
Okay. So you are if you are making edit
ed add editivity false make sure that
this logger has at least one appender.
So this is another example when
additivity is false which is
specifically for appender only if logger
level is missing it will always look
upward upward. So why this example?
Because many engineer got confused the
propagate upward functionality between
appender and level.
So see addit additivity
is associated for only appender. So
whether you make it true or false
whether it has to prop uh propagate
upward or not decided by additivity only
for appender. It has nothing to do with
the level. Level is always always
inherited
from parent. If the current logger is
missing the level, then it always
inherit from parent whether additivity
is true or false. Okay, just a simple
example just to showcase that you should
not get confused in this case. So this
is I have just written multiple log
error one info debug trace. Okay, this
is my logger payment controller. So,
com.concepts.paymentcontroller.
So, I have an appender console. Its task
is to
print the log on the console. This is
the encoder just like format. Now I have
written one logger com.concept. So here
again you might already know what would
have happened. So when you create
com.concept.payment payment controller.
I have one logger for com. I have one
logger for com dot concepts. I have one
logger for my com do.concepts dot
payment controller.
[snorts]
So this logger I have created for com
do.concepts. This one level is one
and appender is console. Appender is
console.
com.concepts.prament Payment controller.
This one
additivity is false
means it should not
move upward propagate upward for
appender. And also it has one appender
console but here level is missing. Level
is missing. I haven't defined the level
here.
And I have one root level is info.
info and appender is console. Appender
is console.
Now what would happen when this all log
statements are logging? So this log
object is payments controller. So it is
starting from here. So
log dot error is this log accepted?
So what is the level of this one? It is
missing here. So it will inherit from
his immediate parent. It does it
immediate parent has the level? Yes.
Wand. So it will use this one wand.
Okay. If its immediate parent also
doesn't have that will inherit from its
parent likewise. But since it's
immediate parent has so it will use that
only want. So
error log dot error will it accept it?
Yes. Because error log statement error
is greater than
uh this one. So this is accepted and log
error is accepted. So accepted logger
now appender will run. So it would be
printed on console and additivity is
false means it will not go upward. So
only one time it will come. Error comes.
Similarly warn is this accepted? Yes I
have the level one. So it is equal. So
that is also accepted. Now for the
accepted log appender will run. So it
will print on console. Additivity is
false. So it will not propagate effort
and it it will not run the parent
appenders. So only one time it will come
error uh info rejected its level is less
than one. Debug rejected trace rejected
because this logger level is one.
Hope you got it.
Okay. So don't get mixed with additivity
true false. What would be the uh flow?
Now add additivity only impact appenders
upward [snorts] propagation. Okay, level
has nothing to do with it. Level if
missing for the logger, it will always
take it from the immediate parent.
Now let's see what all different
appenders logback framework provides.
The one is console appender which we
have already seen the class. So console
so many times what engineer has confused
with the console itself. What exactly is
console? Believe me this confusion
comes. So console appendon means
see different device different console.
So from our Java code perspective, Java
code persceptive
it only
whatever the log you have it only
put it into the output stream which has
the name this output stream name is
standard output H std out.
Now for different device different
console. Okay. So console is you can say
that is specific to devices. Let's say
if you are running on Azure its console
is different. If you are running in
local device your console is your
terminal.
Okay. So if you are running in docker
your console could be different. So for
different device console is different.
But if you go a little bit down, if
somebody asks you, you just say that in
the console appender, our Java code
would only print log or only output the
log in the output stream.
It's open a stream and put into that and
that stream name is a standard output.
Okay. Now, console could be different
for different device. For local run,
it's terminal. For Docker, it's Docker
logging driver. For Azure, it's Azure
Monitor. That's where you will see that
they will read this output stream with
name standard output and whatever data
is coming to the stream it will keep
showing on their monitor. You can say
that.
So it is fast no persistence no out uh
no data which is coming to this stream
it will be saved. It's just coming to
this stream and this whatever the device
you are using their console keeps on
reading this uh stream and they keep
showing it but it's not persistent.
Okay.
So like this we have one console
appender. If you go inside this console
appender class you will see that they
are just opening a stream and putting
into this output stream and that name is
standard output.
The second is file appender.
So it persist log but not safe
production. Please note that don't just
go for file appender. Not safe for
production. Why? I will tell you. Let's
say this is the payment controller. Here
I'm creating a logger object and using
this log object I am creating one
statement.
Now in the logback spring.xml XML uh
configuration start end and then I have
one appender
console already have now here I am
writing a second appender
appender name is file you can give any
name class is file appender that is also
present within our logback framework
okay we don't have to worry about it all
we can give is like file name which we
wanted so here we have this property
file so you can give like okay what's
the package if you want to create and
what's the file name you want to create
so I given app.log
okay generally a standard one so we
create a logs folder and inside that log
folder app.log block file would get
there and I make append equals to true.
So here also we can give false also but
for now I give append true we will see
what does it mean
and then the end code like in the file
whatever the log will go how it will
look like. So this is just the way just
similarly how we were doing in the
console nothing different and append or
close.
Now I here I have written one my logger
which is for paymentscontroller right
com.concepts.p payment controller level
it is accepting is info editivity is
false I don't want to go upward
I have two appender one is console and
one is file so means whatever the log
statement is it will goes to the console
and it will also goes to the file
I have also root level info and the uh
root level has only one console but for
this one doesn't matter because here I
have additivity false so it appender
will never
Now just see this appender [snorts] one
that it will create a file app.log
inside the log package and keep on
appending the log statement whether the
append true or false doesn't matter. It
will keep on appending the log statement
on the file.
Okay. So when append equals to true what
does it mean? It logs are retained when
the application is restarted also. When
you stop the application and start it
again that file is maintained and the
low logs previously stored are still
present. But if you make it false then
what is happen is during restart it will
clean this file and start appending the
log statement again.
Got it? So what's the use of append?
So here now if you run this you will see
that info log is printed on the console
also in the console I got this because
of this appender and also in the file
here if you see log/app.log log this
file got created and it also has this
log statement present
both okay because this logger has two
appender and additivity is false so
that's why it will not look for
appenders for its parent
but it is not good for production why
because your file can grow too big and
you can goes out of space.
Okay. So there need to be control on the
file size.
That's why only file is not production
save. We have something called rolling
file appender which is important.
It persists lock like file but with we
have the way to control the file size.
So it has different policies.
which decide when and how log files are
rotated. Rotated means like okay now you
should have a different file. Now it has
certain policy that hey your file has
reached to a particular limit. Now
whether I have to delete it or whether
you have to create a new file like what
exactly we have to do that we will
define in the policy.
So first policy is timebased rolling
policy. Okay. So here we have the syntax
like percentage D and then
this you can say that it's a
placeholder.
So it controls the rotation frequency.
So let's say if you're using like this
percentage D then year month date. So
rotation will happen daily. So what it
would do is that it will create a new
file daily. It will create a new file
daily. So let's say for 10th of
December, 11th of December, 12th of
December, 13th of December.
Similarly, if you have like year, month,
date and hour, so rotation happen
hourly. So every hour it will create a
new file. 21 0 0 22 0 0 23 0 0 Likewise.
So if you have like year, month, date,
hour, minute, rotation happen every
minute.
Okay. If you have year and month,
rotation happen monthly. So new file
would be created only monthly for
December for January. Likewise,
so for testing purpose I am using
minute. So that in a minute I would get
a file for testing. So I am creating one
appender
name. You can give anything. I am giving
rolling file time base. You can give any
name and also the class is already
present into the log file framework. We
don't have to worry about it. So log
file appender we can use
the file name which we have to uh create
it that we can give. So this file
app.log which is present inside log you
can say that the current logging goes
here. Let's say you are writing for
minute wise minute wise file. So the
current minute data is moved to this
file app.log
and all the archived minute let's say 1
2 3 4 5. Okay. So currently this minute
is going on. So it's this is currently
going on. So it will go into app.log.
Its logs currently will go into here.
But for the past one, okay, those will
go into this file name within a rolling
policy. So now here if you see rolling
policy started rolling policy off. So
inside that we have like file name
pattern. Okay. What's the file name
pattern is like log/
within the log folder itself the same
folder logs I am putting. So here the
file name would be like app-en
the date like this dot log.
Okay. So here if you see it will go like
this app/
year month date till minute. It will go
like this
r minute r minute. So till minute wise
dot log. So it will go like this.
Okay. So that is defined under rolling
policy.
So here if you see rolling policy the
class is which I am using which policy
we are using time based rolling policy.
So here we are using time based rolling
policy that is also present into the
logback framework. We don't have to
write the policy our own that's
implementation is also present. But
let's say if you have to write your own
implementation you can give your own
class and provide the implementation.
But time based rolling policy
implementation is already present. Use
this. All we can give is that okay for
the archive files what's the naming
convention you want for the file name.
So file name pattern is this. I want it.
Maximum history is 30. So read this as
so for minute wise read it as last 30
minutes log will be saved. Okay 30
files. So last 30 minutes would be
saved. If you are using hourly, let's
say if you're using hourly, so read this
30 as last 30 hours data would be saved.
If you're using as day, last 30 days
data would be saved. If you are using
month, last 30 months data would be
saved. Likewise, it's very simple to
always remember that what this max
history means. 30 we are using minute
wise. So last 30 minutes would be saved.
Okay.
And this is the encoder. The same
similar thing like in the file in this
file how this data would be stored what
format.
So I have written my lo uh logger level
is info additivity is false. I don't
want to move upward and I have it
appender console and rolling file time
base. So I'm using this my logger is
using this appender.
So now if you see the output okay so
here if you see I am hitting two times.
So first at 41
R hour r minute I'm using minute wise
right? So 20th hour 41 minute and second
time I am hitting 20th hour 44 minute
okay so currently let's say that this is
the current minute. So the current
minute goes here into app.log log
but the past one
will move to this file like this. Okay.
So 2041. So the past one moved to this
file.
So old log got archived and in this file
name which we have defined here file
name pattern. Okay. And the current
minute. So currently that was the
current minute and that will go into
app.log. log.
Okay. And why apart from file? Why we
are seeing in the console? Because our
logger has both console and the file. So
it is printing on the console and also
it is printing on the file also.
So you got it the rolling file time
based. But again I would say that this
is not production ready.
The best is size plus time based rolling
policy. That's where the size comes into
the picture, right? This is very
important. How big our log file can be
that we have to control. Okay.
So see this one appender.
So here I have created an appender. Give
any name you wanted. The class is the
same rolling file. appender only like we
have the same rolling file appender only
thing is now we are changing the policy
rolling policy
file is again the same the current
active file uh the current r or whatever
the current file will go locks will go
into this file but now our rolling
policy is that
the class which I'm using is size and
time based rolling policy this class
also exists into the framework so now we
using size plus time base.
So file name pattern. So this is for the
archive. So one any file got archived
its name file name format would be log/
appy like this one it will go. Okay
let's say I am using day wise day wise
logging I am following because the same
time based right? So day wise year month
day. So every day new file would be
created. Consider that. Okay. And this
percentage I I will tell you what would
happen. So this is like a file name. Now
maximum file size and total size cap
that is very important. One file how
what's the size of this one file?
Maximum is 100 MB. This one file size
[snorts] could be maximum is 100 MB.
That's all.
Now let's say currently we are going day
wise right let's say today is
18th of December and it's there are lot
of logging very high traffic so logging
goes on and size reach to this 100 MB
but still so it will create another file
the same app- let's say the current will
go into app.log so now the second file
which will it will create it will be
like app.log log and the one which
already achieved this size that would be
like app-en
let's say 2025
12 today is 19 dot I so dot zero dot log
and because that was 100 maximum side
it's already reached its limit and it
created a new file and it's currently
active this logs are happening that's it
that is also reached its 100 MB size
capacity. Okay. So it will create a new
file that will become like an active
app.log active logs will go here and
this one would become archive like app-
2025 - 12 - 19 dot 1.log clock earlier
it was zero then one that's where mod i
comes into the picture because it's a
size based right so even for the one
time base which you are using whether
day or for minute or for like how you
are using the time base based on that we
will create a file for that particular
period a day wise minute wise month wise
so if its size if that file size is
increased then we have to just keep onre
increment the index the same day but it
start from 0.1.2 two and each file could
be like 100 100 MB.
But again the problem is what if
100 100 MB okay we have limit the size
of one file what if there are n number
of files we have to control that also
right so there we can give total size
cap hey maximum you only take 2 GB to
store the logs that's all
so even though 100 100 MB you are
creating so many files but the max
storage we have given is 2 GB
If you have reached till 2GB, so many
files file one, file two, file three on
each 100 MB. Once you reach 2GB, the old
logs would get removed. You you will
always be within 2GB limit only.
Okay. So that is very very important.
And max history is 30. We have already
seen if you are using day wise max 30
days data only it will stored whether
you are within 2GB whether you are
within 100 MB doesn't matter only 30
here we are using day wise only 30 days
data would be stored
okay so here we are creating a rolling
policy and the policy which we are using
is size and time based the file pattern
here is the same thing only thing is we
also we have index associated with
Right.
So let's say we are following a day
level and our file size increases more
than 100 MB. So what it will do is it
will create a new file for the current
log and the file which already reached
its limit it will archive it with this
naming zero. Then if the more files are
coming for the same day.12
each one will have like a 100 MB
maximum it can go 2 GB
okay
so total size cap is like combined all
log files can use this is the size they
can use that's all
so you got it right so this is something
which is production based or production
ready or industry standard best for
production
and what how much total size cap you can
use depend upon your machine capacity
your application traffic okay and also
max history how much back data you want
to keep some companies keep only 21 uh
let's say if they're making day wise
many companies put day wise data uh so
21 days maximum data is available
after that data is deleted.
Okay. But let's say if you are very very
heavy traffic taking API even in the 21
days because of the size capacity you
might lose some data also because let's
say even for one day you reach your 2GB
limit
even for one day your old data logs
would be deleted. So you even though you
have set 21 days but because the total
size cap there is not enough space to
store that much file. So all the all the
logs would get deleted. Okay. So keep
this number depend upon your machine
your application requirement and how
much data logging you want
and the thing is how we can write our
own appender. So we have already seen
that there are already appenders present
right is it possible to write our own
appenders and when do we need it when we
want logs to go our custom destination
like DB or Kafka then there is no
pre-existing appender present which
knows your DB where what's the DB and
all in those cases we have to write our
own appenders very simple nothing much
so create a class give any name class
name let's Say I've given DB appender we
need to extend this class appender base
this one. So i loging event is nothing
uh so appender base is a generic class
you can say and the event here it takes
is i loging event. So i loging event is
nothing but you can say that over one
log statement
one just we are doing right log.info
this converted into log event.
Okay. So this appender base is the class
which we have to extend and it we have
to override this class append. We we
have to override this method append. And
now you can have your own custom logic.
So from this I loging event this one in
this method we have this event object.
This is nothing but your log.info kind
of thing. You can take out a message you
can take out a logger name. You can take
out a time stamp. Okay. And how you want
it to store whether DB or whether Kafka
do it. Okay. So this is how simple is it
to write our own appenders.
All we have to do is extend this
appender base. Then only the logging
framework would be able to identify our
class as an appender
and because since it's all framework all
working on interface right so they will
call append. Okay. So because they need
to follow some structure okay so that's
why we have an append we have this
method we have provided the
implementation
okay our implementation could be default
but we have to follow the framework
now it's very easy in logback spring XML
you can easily create one appender name
whatever the append you want to give DB
appender now the class is this one DB
appender class which we have written the
complete class path com dotconcept dot
custom appender dot db appender.
Now here one more interesting is thing
is you don't need encoder.
Okay, because here we don't know where
the logs are going. It's all present
inside this class. So you decide how
your log going to format would be. So
take out the data from the i loging
event
what and how you want it to show where
you want it to show decide yourself. So
whenever you are using custom appender
you don't need to write an encoder
okay and within your logger you can use
appender reference DB appender this one
and it is using this class very simple
and to be honest I'll tell you in
production generally uh events sometime
publish into let's say Kafka so there we
might have to write a custom appender
like let's say Kafka appender
and inside that we just provide the
implementation.
Okay.
So in the part two this appenders I want
to cover because this is very very
important appenders. Okay. And I hope
all the major things are covered in the
appender nothing left. Now in the next
part I would start with a sync because
currently all everything happening in
the sync
and if you are writing into a DB if you
are writing into a Kafka or if you are
writing in a file those will take time
so your latency might impact. So we have
something very important like a sync
okay so and other thing I will also tell
you about log formats those I will cover
in the next part. So any doubt let me
know we can discuss further and see you
in the next part of it. Bye.